VALERIA KEBETS

Data Scientist | Al Research Scientist | Computational Neuroscienst

@ valkebets@gmail.com

valkebets.github.io

in linkedin.com/in/valkebets

ABOUT

Computational research scientist with over 10 years of academic experience. Experienced in management of large datasets, statistical modeling including machine learning, coding, and conveying complex results to a range of audiences and stakeholders. Seeking to apply my expertise toward devising innovative Al-driven solutions to tackle various challenges.

EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

McGill University

2021 - Present

- Montreal, Canada
- Led several research programs that required management of large datasets (N>10,000), processing of neuroimaging data, statistical data analysis, data visualization, generating research reports, and dissemination to scientific and lay audiences
- Wrote reproducible Python, R, and MATLAB code on McGill University's high-computing systems
- Collaborated with engineers, clinicians and neuroscientists
- Mentored 3 undergraduate and graduate students

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

National University of Singapore

2017 - 2020

- Singapore
- Led research projects to identify shared biological markers across psychiatric disorders using machine learning
- Co-developed an open source toolbox for unsupervised learning
- Co-organized a neuroscience conference and a hackathon
- Taught a course on unsupervised machine learning at the Organization for Human Brain Mapping Annual Meeting
- Assisted with development/maintenance of IRB documents

PhD Candidate

University of Geneva

- **2**012 2016
- Geneva, Switzerland
- Led several research projects to predict early diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease using machine learning and neuroimaging data
- Collected clinical and MRI data in >100 elderly individuals at risk for Alzheimer's disease
- Facilitated collaborations between engineers, neurologists, neuropsychologists and cognitive neuroscientists

CERTIFICATIONS

Deep Learning Specialization (Coursera)

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Neuroscience

University of Geneva

- **2012 2016**
- Geneva, Switzerland
- Advisors: Prof. Dimitri Van De Ville and Prof. Frédéric Assal
- Thesis: Functional imaging markers of the MCI brain in task and at rest: detecting memory and connectivity impairments in prodromal Alzheimer's disease
- Keywords: neuroimaging, machine learning, prediction, biomarker development

M.Sc. in Clinical Neuroscience

University College London

2009 - 2010

London, United Kingdom

- Advisor: Prof. David J. Werring
- Thesis: Neuroimaging correlates of vascular cognitive impairment: prevalence and functional significance of mesial temporal lobe atrophy
- Keywords: neuroimaging, stroke, cognition, radiological marker

B.Sc. in Psychology

University of Geneva

2006 – 2009

Geneva. Switzerland

SKILLS



LANGUAGES

French	••••
English	• • • •
Russian	

SELECTED HONORS AND AWARDS

- Teanne Timmins Costello Fellowship from the Montreal Neurological Institute (40'000 CAD) for the project "A multimodal and dimensional approach to study typical and atypical neurodevelopment" (2022-2023)
- <u>✓</u> Travel awards (total ~6,000 CAD) from the Quebec Bio-Imaging Network, Swiss National Science Foundation, Jean-Falk Vairant Foundation, and Lemanic Neuroscience Doctoral School to attend international conferences (2012-2022)
- Tinalist for Somerfeld-Ziskind Research Award, recognizing outstanding research investigations in biological psychiatry (2021)
- Tuesday Quebec Autism Research Training Fellowship from the Transforming Autism Care Consortium (40'000 CAD) for the project "Neurodevelopmental subtypes informed by hierarchical brain network features" (2021)
- Project grant from the Boninchi Foundation (**75'000 CHF**) for the project "A multimodal marker to predict the progression to Alzheimer's disease" (2016)
- Y Scholarship (10'000 CHF) from the Association Suisse des Femmes Diplômées des Universités (2015)
- Travel Mobility Grant (11'600 CHF) from the Swiss National Science Foundation to visit the Functional Imaging in Neuropsychiatric Disorders Lab, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, USA (2013-2014, 6 months)

SELECTED INVITED TALKS

- Unsupervised machine learning approaches in psychiatric neuroimaging, Organization for Human Brain Mapping Annual Meeting (Singapore 2018, Virtual 2020)
- Identifying transdiagnostic patterns of neural dysfunction, Feindel Brain Imaging Lecture Series, Montreal, Canada (2019)
- Somatosensory-motor dysconnectivity spans multiple transdiagnostic dimensions of psychopathology, Organization for Human Brain Mapping Annual Meeting, Rome, Italy (2019)
- Connectivity-mediated dimensions of psychopathology across mental health and disease, Summer Whistler Scientific Workshop on Brain Functional Organization, Connectivity and Behavior, Noosa, Australia (2019)
- Multivariate and predictive modelling of neural variability in mild cognitive impairment, International Workshop on Pattern Recognition in Neuroimaging, Singapore (2018)
- Predicting pure amnestic mild cognitive impairment conversion to Alzheimer's disease using joint modeling of imaging and clinical data, International Workshop on Pattern Recognition in Neuroimaging, Stanford, CA, USA (2015)
- Structural and functional alterations in presymptomatic Alzheimer's disease revealed by multivariate pattern analysis,
 Annual Meeting of the Society for Neuroscience, San Diego, CA, USA (2013)

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- 1. Park B, **Kebets V**, et al. Multiscale neural gradients reflect transdiagnostic effects of major psychiatric conditions on cortical morphology. *Communications Biology* (2022), 5(1), 1-14.
- 2. Chen J*, Tam A*, **Kebets V**, et al. Shared and unique brain network features predict cognitive, personality, and mental health scores in the ABCD study. *Nature Communications* (2022), 13, 2217.
- 3. Benkarim O, Paquola C, Park B, **Kebets V**, et al. Population heterogeneity in clinical cohorts affects the predictive accuracy of brain imaging. *PLOS Biology (2022), 20(4), e3001627.*
- 4. **Kebets V**, et al. Fronto-limbic neural variability as a transdiagnostic correlate of emotion dysregulation. *Translational Psychiatry (2021), 11, 545.*
- 5. **Kebets V**, et al. Somatosensory-motor dysconnectivity spans multiple transdiagnostic dimensions of psychopathology. *Biological Psychiatry* (2019), 86, 779-91.
- 6. **Kebets V**, et al. Multivariate and predictive modelling of neural variability in mild cognitive impairment. 8th International Workshop on Pattern Recognition in Neuroimaging (2018).
- 7. **Kebets V***, Wegrzyk J*, et al. Identifying motor functional neurological disorder using resting-state functional connectivity. *Neuroimage: Clinical (2018), 17, 163-8.*
- 8. **Kebets V**, et al. Predicting pure amnestic mild cognitive impairment conversion to Alzheimer's disease using joint modeling of imaging and clinical data. 5th International Workshop on Pattern Recognition in Neuroimaging (2015).
- 9. **Kebets V***, Gregoire SM*, Charidimou A*, et al. Prevalence and cognitive impact of medial temporal atrophy in a hospital stroke service: retrospective cohort study. *International Journal of Stroke* (2015), 10(6), 861-7.